https://www.cs.toronto.edu/~sachdeva/sachdeva/sachdeva@cs.toronto.edu

### Research Interests

#### Algorithms, and its connections to optimization and statistics

My research is focused on the design of fast algorithms for problems ranging from theoretical computer science to optimization and statistics. My work brings together tools from convex optimization, numerical linear algebra, data-structures, and approximation theory.

# Appointments

2017 – Present	University of Toronto
2023 – Present	Associate Professor (with tenure), Mathematical and Computational Sciences Associate Professor (with tenure), Department of Computer Science
2017 - 2023	Assistant Professor, Mathematical and Computational Sciences Assistant Professor, Department of Computer Science
2019 – Present	Vector Institute, Faculty Affiliate
Fall 2019	Institute for Advanced Study, Visitor
2016 - 2017	Google, Research Scientist
2014 - 2016	Yale University, Postdoctoral Associate
	Supervisor: Prof. Daniel Spielman

### Education

#### 2008 – 2013 Princeton University

Ph.D., M.A., Department of Computer Science

Advisor: Prof. Sanjeev Arora

Fall 2013 UC Berkeley, Simons Research Fellow

### 2004 - 2008 Indian Institute of Technology Bombay

B.Tech., Department of Computer Science and Engineering

#### Honors and Awards

- 2023 Sloan Research Fellowship (USD 75,000)
- 2023 Frontiers of Science Award at the International Congress on Basic Sciences, Beijing, 2023.
- 2023 Invited long-term Participant for Fall 2023, Simons Institute UC Berkeley
- 2023 Young Alumni Achiever Award, Indian Institute of Technology Bombay (IITB)
- 2023 Invited Plenary Speaker at SODA 2023
- 2022 Best Paper Award at FOCS 2022
- 2022 Ontario Early Researcher Award 2022-27 (CAD 150,000)
- 2021 MITACS Accelerate Grant 2021 (CAD 65,000)
- 2018 NSERC Discovery Grant 2018-2024 (CAD 210,500)
- 2018 Connaught New Researcher Award 2018 (CAD 10,000)
- 2018 Google Faculty Research Award, 2017 (USD 43,335)

- 2013 Simons-Berkeley Research Fellowship, Fall 2013 (USD 26,466)
- 2013 Postdoctoral Research Fellowship by Institute for Computational and Experimental Research in Mathematics (2013-2014, USD 50,000 declined)
- 2008 President of India Gold Medal for topping the class of 2008 (of 500+ students)
- 2008 Jayanti Deshmukh Memorial Gold Medal for being the most outstanding B.Tech. student in the computer science class of 2008 (out of 35 students)
- 2007 Honorable Mention at ACM ICPC World Finals, Tokyo 2007 representing IIT Bombay
- 2004 1st all over India in IIT Entrance Examination 2004 (among 170,000+ students)
- 2004 Bronze Medalist at 36<sup>th</sup> International Chemistry Olympiad (IChO) 2004, Kiel, Germany
- 2004 Aditya Birla Scholarship 2004–08, awarded to only 10 engineering students each year.
- 2004 Dhirubai Ambani Scholarship 2004–08, awarded to top 10 students in Maharashtra state
- 2002 Kishore Vaigyanik Protsahan Yojana (KVPY) fellowship 2002–04. Awarded to around 50 students each year; aimed at promoting research careers in the sciences.

## Monographs

- 2014 Faster Algorithms via Approximation Theory
  - S. Sachdeva, N. K. Vishnoi
  - In Foundations and Trends in Theoretical Computer Science 9.2 (FTTCS) 2014, pp. 125-210

### Refereed Journal Publications

- SICOMP 2020 Graph Sparsification, Spectral Sketches, and Faster Resistance Computation via Short Cycle Decompositions
  - T. Chu, Y. Gao, R. Peng, S. Sachdeva, S. Sawlani, J. Wang
  - SIAM Journal on Computing, FOCS 2018 Special Issue (2020), pp. 85–157
- ORLetters 2016 The mixing time of the Dikin walk in a polytope A simple proof
  - S. Sachdeva, N. Vishnoi
  - In Operations Research Letters, 44.5 (September 2016), pp. 630–634
  - OJAC 2016 An Arithmetic Analogue of Fox's Triangle Removal Argument
    - P. Hatami, S. Sachdeva, M. Tulsiani
    - In Online Journal of Analytic Combinatorics 11 (OJAC) 2016
  - Algorithmica Provable ICA with Unknown Gaussian Noise, and Implications for Gaussian Mixtures and
    - 2015 Autoencoders
      - S. Arora, R. Ge, A. Moitra, S. Sachdeva
      - In Algorithmica 72.1 (May 2015), pp. 215–236
  - SIDMA 2015 Inapproximability of Minimum Vertex Cover on k-Uniform k-Partite Hypergraphs
    - V. Guruswami, S. Sachdeva, R. Saket
    - In SIAM Journal on Discrete Mathematics 29.1 (SIDMA) 2015, pp. 36–58
    - CGF 2014 Greedy Geometric Algorithms for Collection of Balls, with Applications to Geometric Approximation and Molecular Coarse-Graining
      - F. Cazals, T. Dreyfus, S. Sachdeva, N. Shah
      - In Computer Graphics Forum 33–6, 2014
  - TCBB 2011 On the Characterization and Selection of Diverse Conformational Ensembles with Applications to Flexible Docking
    - S. Loriot, S. Sachdeva, K. Bastard, C. Prevost, F. Cazals
    - In Computational Biology and Bioinformatics, IEEE/ACM Transactions on 8.2 (TCBB) 2011, pp. 487–498

# Refereed Conference / Workshop Publications

- FOCS 2023 A Deterministic Almost-Linear Time Algorithm for Minimum-Cost Flow Jvd. Brand, L. Chen, R. Kyng, Y. P. Liu, R. Peng, M. P. Gutenberg, S. Sachdeva, A. Sidford
- SPAA 2023 A Simple and Efficient Parallel Laplacian Solver S. Sachdeva, Y. Zhao
- SOSA 2023 A Simple Framework for Finding Balanced Sparse Cuts via APSP L. Chen, R. Kyng, M. Probst Gutenberg, S. Sachdeva
- SODA 2023 A New Approach to Estimating Effective Resistances & Counting Spanning Trees in Expanders L. Li, S. Sachdeva
- FOCS 2022 Maximum Flow and Minimum-Cost Flow in Almost-Linear Time
  L. Chen, R. Kyng. Y. P. Liu, R. Peng, M. P. Gutenberg, S. Sachdeva
  Best Paper Award at FOCS 2022
  Frontiers of Science Award 2023
  Invited to J.ACM
  Invited to Highlight of Algorithms 2023
- ICML 2022 A Convergent and Dimension-Independent Min-Max Optimization Algorithm V. Keswani, O. Mangoubi, S. Sachdeva, N. K. Vishnoi
- SODA 2022 Nested Dissection Meets IPMs: Planar Min-Cost Flow in Nearly Linear Time S. Dong, Y. Gao, G. Goranci, Y.T. Lee, R. Peng, S. Sachdeva, G. Ye
- NeurIPS 2021 Unifying Width-Reduced Methods for Quasi-Self-Concordant Optimization D. Adil, B. Bullins, S. Sachdeva
- ICALP 2021 Almost-linear-time Weighted  $\ell_p$ -norm Solvers in Slightly Dense Graphs via Sparsification. D. Adil, B. Bullins, R, Kyng, S. Sachdeva
- NeurIPS 2020 Regularized linear autoencoders recover the principal components, eventually X. Bao, J. Lucas, S. Sachdeva, R. Grosse
  - ICML 2020 Faster Graph Embeddings via Coarsening
    M. Fahrbach, G. Goranci, S. Sachdeva, R. Peng, C. Wang
  - SODA 2020 Faster p-norm minimizing flows, via smoothed q-norm problems D. Adil, S. Sachdeva
- NeurIPS 2019 Fast, Provably convergent IRLS Algorithm for p-norm Linear Regression D. Adil, R. Peng, S. Sachdeva
- NeurIPS 2019 Which Algorithmic Choices Matter at Which Batch Sizes? Insights From a Noisy Quadratic Model
  G. Zhang, L. Li, Z. Nado, J. Martens, S. Sachdeva, G. Dahl, C. Shallue, R. Grosse
  - STOC 2019 Flows in Almost Linear Time via Adaptive Preconditioning R. Kyng, R. Peng, S. Sachdeva, D. Wang
- AISTATS 2019 Improved Semi-Supervised Learning with Multiple Graphs
  K. Viswanathan\*, S. Sachdeva\*, A. Tomkins, S. Ravi (\*=equal contribution)
  - SODA 2019 Iterative Refinement for  $\ell_p$ -norm Regression D. Adil, R. Kyng, R. Peng, S. Sachdeva
  - SODA 2019 Short Cycles via Low-Diameter Decompositions Y. P. Liu, S. Sachdeva, Z. Yu

- FOCS 2018 Graph Sparsification, Spectral Sketches, and Faster Resistance Computation, via Short Cycle Decompositions
   T. Chu, Y. Gao, R. Peng, S. Sachdeva, S. Sawlani, J. Wang
   Invited to SIAM Journal on Computing Special Issue
   Invited to Highlights of Algorithms 2019
- ITCS 2018 Convergence Results for Neural Networks via Electrodynamics
   R. Panigrahy, A. Rahimi, S. Sachdeva, Q. Zhang
- SODA 2018 Near-optimal approximation algorithm for simultaneous Max-Cut A. Bhangale, S. Khot, S. Kopparty, S. Sachdeva, D. Thiruvenkatachari
- STOC 2017 Sampling Random Spanning Trees Faster than Matrix Multiplication D. Durfee, R. Kyng, J. Peebles, A. B. Rao, S. Sachdeva
- SODA 2017 A framework for analyzing resparsification algorithms R.Kyng, J. Pachocki, R. Peng, S. Sachdeva
- FOCS 2016 Approximate Gaussian Elimination for Laplacians: Fast, Sparse, and Simple R. Kyng, S. Sachdeva Invited to Highlights of Algorithms 2017
- STOC 2016 Sparsified Cholesky and Multigrid Solvers for Connection Laplacians R. Kyng, Y. T. Lee, R. Peng, S. Sachdeva, and D. A. Spielman
- NIPS 2015 Fast, Provable Algorithms for Isotonic Regression in all  $\ell_p$ -norms R. Kyng, A. B. Rao, S. Sachdeva
- COLT 2015 Algorithms for Lipschitz Learning on Graphs R. Kyng, A. B. Rao, S. Sachdeva, D. A. Spielman
- ICALP 2015 Simultaneous Approximation of Constraint Satisfaction Problems
  A. Bhangale, S. Kopparty, S. Sachdeva
  - CCC 2013 Optimal Inapproximability for Scheduling Problems via Structural Hardness for Hypergraph Vertex Cover
    S. Sachdeva, R. Saket
- STOC 2012 Approximating the Exponential, the Lanczos Method and an  $\widetilde{O}(m)$ -Time Spectral Algorithm for Balanced Separator

  L. Orecchia, S. Sachdeva, N. K. Vishnoi
- NIPS 2012 Provable ICA with Unknown Gaussian Noise, and Implications for Gaussian Mixtures and Autoencoders
  S. Arora, R. Ge, A. Moitra, S. Sachdeva
  Invited to Algorithmica Special Issue for Machine Learning
  - EC 2012 Finding Overlapping Communities in Social Networks: Towards a Rigorous Approach S. Arora, R. Ge, S. Sachdeva, G. Schoenebeck
- RANDOM 2012 Testing Permanent Oracles Revisited S. Arora, A. Bhattacharyya, R. Manokaran, S. Sachdeva
- APPROX 2011 Nearly Optimal NP-Hardness of Vertex Cover on k-Uniform k-Partite Hypergraphs S. Sachdeva, R. Saket

#### Theses

- 2013 New Results in the Theory of Approximation: Fast Graph Algorithms and Inapproximability Ph.D. Thesis, Princeton University. Advised by Sanjeev Arora
- 2008 On the Hardness of Approximating Vertex Cover B.Tech. Thesis, IIT Bombay. Advised by Sundar Vishwanathan

# Supervision

Graduate students:

Lawrence Li (Ph.D. student, UToronto, 2020–)

Yibin Zhao (Ph.D. student, UToronto, 2020-)

Hantang Li (MScAC student, UToronto, 2023–)

Anthony Rinaldi (MScAC student, UToronto, 2023-)

Deepkamal Kaur Gill (MScAC student, UToronto, 2022–2023)

Hao Zhang (MScAC student, UToronto, 2021–22)

Deeksha Adil (M.Sc. student, UToronto, 2017–2019, Ph.D. student, 2019–2022)

Postdocs:

Gramoz Goranci (2020–2021). Assistant Professor at U. Vienna.

 $Undergraduate\ students$ :

Sasha Voitovych (UToronto, Winter 2023)

Anvith Thudi (UToronto, 2022–)

Devansh Ranade (UToronto, 2020–2021)

Jack McKinney (UToronto, Summer 2020)

Zejun Yu (UToronto, Summer 2018)

Mentees:

Yang P. Liu (Summer 2018). Graduate student, Stanford.

Joshua Wang (Summer 2017). Research Scientist, Google.

Qiuyi (Richard) Zhang (Fall 2016). Software Engineer, Google.

Xiao Shi (Fall 2015). Software Engineer, Facebook.

## Media Coverage

2022 Quanta Magazine, Researchers Achieve 'Absurdly Fast' Algorithm for Network Flow Quanta Science Podcast, — : Apple, Google, Spotify

### **Talks**

Almost-linear time Algorithms for Max-Flow and More

- Feb 2023 Princeton University, Theory Lunch
- Jan 2023 Symposium on Discrete Algorithms (SODA), Invited Plenary talk
- Dec 2022 Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, STCS Seminar
- Oct 2022 Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton
- May 2022 Simons Institute for Theory of Computing, 10th Anniversary Symposium
- May 2022 University of Toronto, Theory Seminar
- Apr 2022 University of Texas Austin, Theory Seminar
- Mar 2022 University of Waterloo, Theory Seminar
- Mar 2022 IRIF Paris, Algorithms and Complexity Seminar

Improved  $\ell_p$ -norm Optimization via Iterative Refinement

- Apr 2021 University of Washington. Theory seminar
- Feb 2021 Carnegie Mellon University, Theory seminar
- Sep 2019 Indian Institute of Technology Bombay, Seminar
- Sep 2019 Indian Institute of Technology Delhi, Seminar
- Feb 2019 Northwestern University, Theory seminar
- Feb 2019 University of Chicago / Toyota Technological Institute, Theory Seminar
- Feb 2019 Google Mountain View, STOCA Workshop

Faster p-norm minimizing flows, via smoothed q-norm problems

Jan 2020 Symposium on Discrete Algorithms (SODA)

Fast IRLS Algorithms for p-norm regression

May 2020 University of Toronto, Fuji Co-creation Lab seminar

	Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton Yale University, Theory Seminar
	Graph Sparsifiers via Short-Cycle Decompositions Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton Highlights of Algorithms, Copenhagen
Oct 2018	Approximate Gaussian Elimination and Applications Laplacian 2.0 Workshop, FOCS 2018
Jun 2018 Nov 2017 Jun 2017 Mar 2017 Nov 2016 Sep 2016 Sep 2016	Fast Approximate Gaussian Elimination for Laplacians Dagstuhl Seminar, Germany, High Performance Graph Algorithms Canada Applied and Industrial Mathematics Society (CAIMS), Toronto University of Waterloo, Department Seminar Highlights of Algorithms, Berlin Simons Collaboration on Algorithms & Geometry, New York TOCA-SV, Stanford University TCS Plus Seminar Harvard University, Theory of Computation Seminar Boston University, Theory Lunch
Apr 2016 Mar 2016	Fast Algorithms for Optimization and Learning on Graphs Google, New York Computer Science Colloquium, Purdue University Department of Computer Science Lecture, University of Toronto, Canada Computer Science Seminar, University of Colorado Boulder
	Regression on Graphs – Lipschitz and Isotonic University of Texas Austin, Simons Seminar University of Chicago, Scientific and statistical computing seminar
Jul 2015 Jul 2015 Jul 2015 May 2015	Lipschitz Learning on Graphs Carnegie Mellon University, Theory seminar Indian Institute of Technology Bombay, CS department Seminar EPFL (École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne) INF department seminar Conference on Learning Theory (COLT) University of California San Diego, CS department theory seminar Yale University, Statistics department seminar
	Triangle Removal in Groups Simons Institute for Theory of Computing, Real analysis seminar Institute for Advanced Study (IAS) Computer science/discrete mathematics seminar
Aug 2013	Generalizations of KKL Theorem and Friedgut's Junta Theorem Simons Institute for Theory of Computing, UC Berkeley, Real analysis workshop
Jun 2013	Hardness for Scheduling Problems Conference on Computational Complexity (CCC)
Aug 2012 May 2012	Near-linear Time Algorithms for Balanced Separator Rutgers University, DIMACS/CS theoretical computer science seminar University of Washington, ETP theory connections Symposium on Theory of Computing (STOC) Institute for Advanced Study (IAS) Computer science/discrete mathematics seminar
Aug 2012	Testing Permanent Oracles International Workshop on Randomization and Computation (RANDOM)

# Professional Service

Editor:

 $2021\;$  ACM Transactions of Algorithms (TALG) SODA 2021 special issue

- 2019 SIAM Journal on Computing (SICOMP) STOC 2019 special issue
  - Program Committee:

Organizer:

- 2023 Innovations in Theoretical Computer Science (ITCS) 2024
- 2023 IEEE Foundations of Computer Science (FOCS) 2023
- 2022 European Symposium on Algorithms (ESA) 2022
- 2022 ACM Symposium on Theory of Computing (STOC) 2022
- 2021 ACM-SIAM Symposium on Discrete Algorithms (SODA) 2021
- $2019\,$  ACM Symposium on Theory of Computing (STOC)  $2019\,$
- 2018 Workshop 'Laplacians 2.0', FOCS 2018, Paris, France

 $\begin{array}{l} Conference\ Reviewing:\ STOC\ (2014–2020),\ FOCS\ (2014–2021),\ SODA\ (2012–2020),\ CCC\ 2020,\ COLT\ 2018–2019,\ ESA\ 2019,\ NeurIPS\ /\ NIPS\ (2016–2021),\ ICML\ (2018–2020),\ ITCS\ (2013,\ 2020),\ ICLR\ 2018,\ ICALP\ (2012,\ 2018–2019),\ APPROX\ (2013,\ 2017),\ RANDOM\ (2019,\ 2014),\ WADS\ 2017,\ SPAA\ 2017,\ FSTTCS\ (2011,\ 2013),\ LATIN\ 2012,\ QIC\ 2015 \end{array}$ 

Journal Reviewing: Siam Journal on Discrete Mathematics (SIDMA), Algorithmica, Theory of Computing, Siam Journal on Computing (SICOMP)

# Teaching Experience

#### Assistant Professor, University of Toronto

- Fall 2022 Instructor for CSC 2240H: Graphs, Matrices, and Optimization
- Fall 2022 Instructor for CSC 373H5: Algorithm Design and Analysis
- Winter 2021 Instructor for CSC 2421H: Graphs, Matrices, and Optimization
- Winter 2021 Instructor for CSC 263H5: Data Structures and Analysis
  - Fall 2020 Instructor for CSC 373H5: Algorithm Design and Analysis
- Winter 2020 Instructor for CSC 263H5: Data Structures and Analysis
- Winter 2019 Instructor for CSC 263H5: Data Structures and Analysis
  - Fall 2018 Instructor for CSC 2421H: Graphs, Matrices, and Optimization
- Winter 2018 Instructor for CSC 263H5: Data Structures and Analysis
  - Fall 2017 Instructor for CSC 2421H: Fast Algorithms via Continuous Methods

#### Lecturer, Yale University

Spring 2015 Lecturer for CPSC 665: An Algorithmist's toolkit

Designed and taught a full course on advanced algorithms (2 lectures a week)

55% of students rated the course excellent (highest rating)

#### Teaching Assistant, Princeton University

- Winter 2010 Assistant in Instruction for COS 433: Cryptography
  - Fall 2009 Assistant in Instruction for COS 340: Reasoning About Computation

# **Professional Experience**

- Summer 2012 Toyota Technological Institute, Chicago, IL
  - Research Intern. Supervisor: Yury Makarychev
- Summer 2011 Microsoft Research India, Bangalore, India
  - Research Intern. Supervisor: Nisheeth K. Vishnoi
- Summer 2007 INRIA, Sophia-Antipolis, France
  - Research Intern. Supervisor: Frederic Cazals

### Sushant Sachdeva

Summer 2006 ETH, Zurich, Switzerland

Research Intern. Supervisor: Riko Jacob